Finding Aid for the Cole Family Papers LSC.0217
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Correspondence of the Cole Family, 1846-1940; (Approximately 1700 pieces)
  - Correspondence and Papers of Lucretia Cole
    - Diaries of Lucretia Cole., 1873-1890; 3 vol. and 5pp. (Box 52, Folder 3)
      Volume of 1873 concerning the Grants, especially Jessie Grant, family of General Irvin McDowell, H.H. Bancroft, entries to 1880. vol. 1880 including sketch by Jessie Grant, references to the McDowells and Grants, Sharons, reception for President Hayes, entries to 1881, many pages missing and mutilated. vol. 1887 references to members of the Cleveland Cabinet, wife of Senator Jones, Robert Peary, Grover Cleveland, Roscoe Conkling. Unbound pages of diary of 1890 concerning voyage to Europe.
    - Papers of Lucretia Cole., 10 pieces (Box 53)
      Holograph notes, statements, and papers concerning libraries, bookbinding, and related subjects.
    - Miscellaneous Papers of Lucretia Cole., 35 pieces. (Box 54)
      Notes on Waring and other geneologies, invitations from Presidents Johnson to Roosevelt, references to Lincoln picture, passports.
  - Correspondence and Papers of George T. Cole
    - George T. Cole to Olive Cole., 1894-1905; 110 pieces. (Box 55, Folder 1)
      Letters written from Chicago and various places in Europe, with references to painting and visiting the Potter Palmer and George Pullman families.
    - Various persons to George T. Cole., 1914-1937; 48 pieces. (Box 55, Folder 2)
      Letters concerning the Cole estate and property, 9 letters from Charles A. Siringo concerning his western fiction, letter to Tom Mix concerning his portrait, letters concerning Arizona.
    - Papers of George T. Cole., 55 pieces. (Box 55, Folder 3)
      Photographs of Cole and of his paintings including one of Tom Mix, articles relating to shows of his work.
- Business Papers of Cornelius Cole and the Cole Family
  - Papers and Documents Pertaining to Cole Family Real Estate, 1877-1899; (Approximately 500 pieces)
    - Correspondence, documents and papers concerning Cole family real estate., 1877-1888; 44 pieces. (Box 56, Folder 1)
      Subjects include La Brea rancho, San Bernardino desert lands, lots sold to Bishop Francis Mora. Letter from nephew David Cole.
    - Correspondence, documents and papers concerning Cole family real estate., 1888-1893; 60 pieces. (Box 56, Folder 2)
      Subjects include mortgages and loans on Cole ranch, Sacramento county, property used by the Los Angeles county railroad, abstract of disposition of land granted to J.A. Sutter.
    - Correspondence, documents and papers concerning Cole family real estate., 1889-1890; 15 pieces. (Box 56, Folder 3)
      Subjects include Tule swamp lands for reclamation in Sacramento county.
    - Correspondence, documents and papers concerning Cole family real estate., 1889-1894; 45 pieces. (Box 56, Folder 4)
      Subject: litigation with L.T. Garnsey over the Cole Ranch.
    - Correspondence, documents and papers concerning Cole family real estate., 1893-1899; 55 pieces. (Box 56, Folder 5)
      Subjects centered about Colegrove, Hollywood development.
  - Papers and Documents Pertaining to Cole Family Real Estate, 1900-1916
    - Correspondence, documents and papers concerning Cole family real estate, [Oil land]., 1900-1901; 80 pieces. (Box 57, Folder 1)
      Materials relative to the leasing and exploration of Cole lands for oil and other minerals by local petroleum companies.
    - Correspondence, documents and papers concerning Cole family real estate., 1902-1904; 50 pieces. (Box 57, Folder 2)
      Subject: Property in Hollywood, Colegrove development, loans and mortgages.
    - Correspondence, documents and papers concerning Cole family real estate., 1904-1911; 30 pieces. (Box 57, Folder 3)
      Subjects: Lots in Hollywood, loans and development, Colegrove Water Company.
    - Correspondence, documents and papers concerning Cole family real estate., 1912-1916; 60 pieces. (Box 57, Folder 4)
      Subjects: expansion of property in Hollywood, development and improvement of Griffith Park, Colegrove, etc.
  - Papers and Documents Pertaining to Business Matters of Members of the Cole Family, 1884-1916
    - Papers and documents concerning business matters of Schuyler, Cornelius and Willoughby Cole., 1895-1910; 50 pieces. (Box 58, Folder 1)
      Subjects: West Los Angeles Water Company, Hollywood High School, Colegrove.
    - Personal promissory notes, receipts, checks, 1884-1916; 60 pieces. (Box 58, Folder 2)
      Includes receipts from litigants in Alabama claims cases.
  - Miscellaneous Commercial and Real Estate Papers, 1896-1916
    - Commercial receipts and bills of sale., 1896-1910; 100 pieces. (Box 59, Folder 1)
    - Commercial receipts and bills of sale., 1911-1916; 200 pieces. (Box 59, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous maps of real estate developments in Los Angeles and Southern California., 50 pieces. (Folder 3)
  - Papers and Documents Pertaining to Commercial Acquisitions and Transferals By Cornelius Cole and the Cole family, 1862-1923
    - Commercial receipts and bills of sale, 1865-1923; 220 pieces. (Box 23, Folder 1)
      Hotel bills, building and maintenance orders and bills, personal purchases.
    - Documents concerning real estate of the Cole family, 1862-1923; 60 pieces. (Box 23, Folder 2)
      Deeds, agreements, transferals, mortgages, court decisions.
  - Papers and Documents Pertaining to the Finances of the Cole Family, 1850-1926
    - Correspondence, stock certificates, accounts of Cole family finances., 1864-1926; 42 pieces. (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, tax receipts, real estate maps., 1889-1924; 80 pieces. (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - Personal promissory notes, receipts, checks., 1850-1924; 120 pieces. (Box 24, Folder 3)
- Writings of Cornelius and Olive Cole and the Cole Family
  - Manuscript of the Memoirs of Cornelius Cole
    - Manuscript of Preface through Chapter 5. (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - Manuscript of Chapter 6 through Chapter 16. (Box 25, Folder 2)
    - Manuscript of Chapter 17 through Chapter 26. (Box 25, Folder 3)
    - Manuscript of Chapter 27 through Chapter 41. (Box 25, Folder 4)
    - Manuscript and typescript drafts: fragments. (Box 25, Folder 5)
  - Diaries of Cornelius Cole, 1863-1923
    - 57 pocket-size volumes with sporadic and sparse entries (Box 26)
      Concerning personal finances, appointments, local events in California, and Washington, D.C. There are brief references to national affairs, Presidents, Senators, elections. The most significant entries are in vol. 1863-1864, in which there is mention of the fortifications around Washington, D.C., a description of a visit to General Ulysses S. Grant and his statements concerning army campaigns, and the entry in vol. 1867 which is a transcription from an earlier diary (missing) concerning a trip made by Cole through Virginia in July, 1865, with details of the conditions there immediately after the war. No volumes for the period, 1872-1875.
    - Diaries (Box 26)
      1858, references to Kansas and slavery
      1860, references to Ralston, Crocker, Lincoln, Field, campaign of 1860
      1864, 1866, references to the Blairs, Kasson, Sewards, Welles, Halleck, Doolittle, Colfax, Sherman, Criswell, Morgan, Halin, Chase, Sumner, Washburne, Johnson, interviews with Lincoln, reference to Grants 1869, references to San Domingo trip, Grant, Fish
      1870, references to Low, Grant, Cabinet members, C.P. Huntington.
  - Writings of Cornelius Cole, 1850-1867
    - Drafts of speeches, so labeled or determined, and printed copies of speeches by Cornelius Cole, 1860-1922; 44 pieces. (Box 27, Folder 1)
      Subjects include Stephen A. Douglas, Andrew Johnson, Reconstruction, currency issues, the Pacific railroad, the China Mail bill, whiskey revenue in California, Lincoln's Gettysburg Address.
    - Drafts and copies of articles, essays, legal statements by Cornelius Cole, 1850-1862; 42 pieces. (Box 27, Folder 2)
      Subjects include the Pacific railroad, Stephen A. Douglas, crisis in Kansas, Republican nominations 1856 and 1860, extension of slavery, policy of James Buchanan, Chinese immigrants, legal briefs, documents and letters concerning the Slave Extradition case in Sacramento, 1852.
    - Drafts of articles and legislation by Cornelius Cole, 1863-1869; 7 pieces. (Box 27, Folder 3)
      Subjects include the Central Pacific and other California railroads, the appointive power of the President, plans of the Republican party, an interview with William H. Seward concerning Russian and Pacific affairs.
  - Writings of Cornelius Cole, 1870-1919
    - Drafts of articles, legislation, and statements by Cornelius Cole, 1870-1879; 14 pieces. (Box 28, Folder 1)
      Subjects include A.A. Sargent, California swamp lands, railroads in Arizona and the southwest, Pacific Mail Steamship Company, currency issues, papers and documents concerning the Samoan Islands project, 1872-1873.
    - Drafts of articles, essays, and statements by Cornelius Cole, 1880-1899; 35 pieces. (Box 28, Folder 2)
      Subjects include irrigation of lands, the overland trip to California in 1849, William McKinley, Collis P. Huntington, the Pacific railroad, National Banks, Los Angeles Harbor.
    - Articles, essays, and statements by Cornelius Cole,. Subjects include William H. Taft, Hay-Pauncefote Treaty, Lincoln's Emancipation Proclamation, the Republican party, Alaska., 1900-1913; 18 pieces. (Box 28, Folder 3)
    - Drafts and printed copies of articles, essays, and statements by Cornelius Cole, 1914-1919; 152 pieces. (Box 28, Folder 4)
      Subjects include the causes and course of World War I, the character and policies of Woodrow Wilson, relations with England and Germany, Theodore Roosevelt, Collis P. Huntington, Robert E. Lee, the League of Nations, California lemon industry and the tariff, Hiram Johnson, the Central Pacific railroad, the Progressive party.
  - Writings of Cornelius Cole, 1894-1912
    - Drafts of articles and statements by Cornelius Cole, 1894-1903; 22 pieces. (Box 60, Folder 1)
      Subjects include Los Angeles Harbor controversy, and Hollywood High School.
    - Drafts of articles and statements by Cornelius Cole, 1909-1911; 18 pieces. (Box 60, Folder 2)
      Subject: California citrus industry and the citrus tariff legislation.
    - Drafts of articles and statements by Cornelius Cole, 1909-1912; 16 pieces. (Box 60, Folder 3)
      Subject: The senatorial campaign of A.G. Spaulding.
    - Writings of Cornelius Cole., 60 pieces. (Box 60, Folder 4-5)
      Statements, drafts, fragments concerning Cole family, Chinese Exclusion, interview with Charles Daniels a 49er, Apaches, bankers, C.P. Huntington, Cleveland and Blaine, A.A. Sargent, a narrative of New Mexico, and of California Indians.
  - Writings of Cornelius Cole, 1874-1924
    - Drafts and copies of articles, essays, and statements by Cornelius Cole, 1920-1924; 46 pieces. (Box 29, Folder 1)
      Subjects include disarmament, Hiram Johnson, Ku Klux Klan, Reparations, Warren G. Harding, Alaska, Lincoln's Gettysburg Address, Pony Express days.
    - Bound essays by Cornelius Cole., 4 vol. (Box 29, Folder 2)
      General note
      [N.B. For additional writings see Box 37 (Oversize)]
      vol.1 includes essays on gravitation, the cause of heat and light, inhabitants of the spheres.
      vol.2 includes essay on the curious mounds of California.
      vol.3 includes essays of Cornelius Cole's first participation in the Van-Buren-Cass campaign in 1848 in New York State, the Democratic party, abolition, experiences with Mark Hopkins in 1852 during the Negro Extradition case in Sacramento, mining in early California, lynching at Jackson, California in 1849, Cole's ancestry, Thaddeus Stevens, C.P. Huntington, John Brown, Lincoln, slavery, capital and labor, Hannibal Hamlin's humor.
      vol.4 includes essays on currency issues, World War I.
    - Literary Pieces by Cornelius Cole, n.d.
      - 2 sets of typescripts bound in 2 vol. tentatively entitled Proverbial Couplets by A Pioneer [or by Grandfather; or by An Octogenarian]., 250pp. each vol. (Box 30)
      - 22 pocket-size volumes of couplets by Cornelius Cole. Some of them are political in subject. (Box 31, Folder 1)
      - 5 tablet-size volumes of couplets and fables by Cornelius Cole. (Box 31, Folder 2)
      - Manuscript fragments of couplets, fables by Cornelius Cole., 10 pieces. (Box 31, Folder 3)
      - Fables by Cornelius Cole. Manuscript and typescript copies., 8 pieces. (Box 31, Folder 4)
      - Miscellaneous literary pieces. Most of the pieces are philosophical in subject., 28 pieces. (Box 31, Folder 5)
  - Diaries and Reminiscences of Olive Cole, 1851-1918
    - Diaries: vol.., 1851-1857; 4 vol. (Box 32, Folder 1)
      Entries concerning family and life in New York State and in California, Republican organization and politics, the election of 1856, lists of callers which includes Leland Stanford and Mark Hopkins, San Francisco city elections. vol. 1866-1868: Entries concerning the administration and impeachment of Andrew Johnson, Reconstruction, the 38th Congress, visit to Mt. Vernon, Virginia, George W. Cole's trial, debates on redemption of gold bonds, Benjamin Butler, Newton Booth, Grant, George Boutwell, Vennie Ream, sculptress. vol. 1869-1871: Entries concerning the inauguration of Grant, his personality, Cornelius Cole's political appointments, Decoration Day in 1869, the Franco-Prussian War, W.P. Fessenden, Lyman Trumbull, Jacob Cox, Babcock, Andrew Johnson, Mrs. Belknap, Commissioners for the Alabama Claims, Charles Sumner, Hamilton Fish, Zachariah Chandler. vol. 1872-1877: Entries concerning the election of Newton Booth, influence of the Central Pacific railroad, visit to Yosemite Valley, influence of capitalists on Grant and Congress, rumor of war with Spain over Cuba, cases of Cornelius Cole in the U.S. Supreme Court, San Francisco affairs, death of W.C. Ralston, the Theodore Tilton-Henry Ward Beecher case, Centennial Exposition.
    - Reminiscences of Olive Cole., 16 pieces. (Box 32, Folder 2)
      Subjects include her early life in New York State in the 1850s, early California, the impeachment of Andrew Johnson, Grant, Mark Twain.
  - Writings of Olive Cole and Members of the Cole Family, 1873-1918
    - Articles and essays by Olive Cole., 80 pieces. (Box 32, Folder 1)
      Subjects include the World's Columbian Exposition, the Republican party, Water and Power bonds, women's suffrage.
    - Literary pieces by Olive Cole., 6 pieces. (Box 32, Folder 2)
      Poems and a short story.
    - Clippings of articles by Gilbert M. Cole and Seward Cole,., 1891-1901; 5 pieces. (Box 32, Folder 3)
    - Olive Cole's Geneological Papers. (Box 71, Box 72)
    - Diaries of Reginald H. Jones (C. Cole's Son-In-Law). (Box 73)
- Miscellaneous Papers and Objects, 1833-1943
  - Newspaper Clippings Concerning Cornelius Cole, Olive Cole and Members of the Cole Family, 1885-1934
    - Newspaper clippings, 1903-1924; 150 pieces. (Box 34, Othertype 1)
      Concerning Cornelius Cole. References to Lincoln.
    - Newspaper clippings, 1903-1924; 150 pieces. (Box 34, Othertype 2)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1911-1918; 42 pieces. (Box 34, Othertype 3)
      Concerning Olive Cole.
    - Newspaper clippings, 1885-1934; 70 pieces. (Box 34, Othertype 4)
      Concerning members of the Cole family. References to Grant and Colfax.
    - Newspaper clippings concerning the biography of Cornelius Cole by Catherine C. Phillips,., 1929-1931; 14 pieces. (Box 34, Othertype 5)
  - Newspaper Clippings Concerning Various Political Subjects, 1844-1880
    - Clippings from California and other newspapers, 1844-1860; 60 pieces. (Box 35, Othertype 1)
      Concerning slavery, the Kansas crisis, Roger B. Taney's Dred Scot decision, James Buchanan, the Democratic party, David C. Broderick, the Republican party in California.
    - Clippings from California and Washington, D.C. newspapers, 1860-1865; 18 pieces. (Box 35, Othertype 2)
      Concerning the military and political events of the Civil War, the death of Stephen A. Douglas.
    - Clippings from California and Washington, D.C. newspapers, 1865-1869; 25 pieces. (Box 35, Othertype 3)
      Concerning the administration and impeachment of Andrew Johnson, politics in California, the election of Grant, the death of Thaddeus Stevens.
    - Clippings from California and Washington, D.C. newspapers, 1870-1880; 30 pieces. (Box 35, Othertype 4)
      Concerning the administration of Grant, society in Washington, D.C., the death of Andrew Johnson, the Central Pacific Railroad.
  - Newspaper Clippings Concerning Various Political Subjects, 1846-1926
    - Clippings from California and Washington, D.C. newspapers, 1870-1880; 85 pieces. (Box 36, Othertype 1)
      Concerning the Senatorial career of Cornelius Cole, politics and legislation in California, Confederate cruiser Shenandoah.
    - Clippings from California newspapers, 1870-1880; 14 pieces. (Box 36, Othertype 2)
      Concerning the Central Pacific Railroad, its finances and construction.
    - Clippings from California newspapers, 1872; 20 pieces. (Box 36, Othertype 3)
      Concerning the Goat Island, San Francisco, bill.
    - Clippings from California newspapers, 1880; 180 pieces. (Box 36, Othertype 4)
      Concerning the forged Garfield-Chinese letter and the election of 1880.
    - Clippings from California newspapers, 1890-1909; 25 pieces. (Box 61, Othertype 5)
      Concerning the Populist party, currency issues, William McKinley, Los Angeles Harbor, Spanish-American War, the Alaska Purchase, Lincoln, Grant, the survivors of the impeachment of Andrew Johnson.
    - Clippings from California newspapers concerning the election of, candidates and the campaign., 1912; 6 pieces. (Box 36, Othertype 6)
    - Clippings and papers from various political campaigns in California and the U.S., 1852-1922; 65 pieces. (Box 36, Othertype 7)
      Sample ballots, lists of candidates, advertisements.
    - Clippings from California newspapers, 1914-1919; 28 pieces. (Box 36, Othertype 8)
      Concerning World War I, American foreign policy, election of 1916.
    - Clippings from California newspapers, 1906-1926; 28 pieces. (Box 36, Othertype 9)
      Concerning state and local history.
    - New York State newspapers., 1846-1913; 7 pieces. (Box 36, Othertype 10)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, Volumes, and Documents, 1863-1923; (Oversize)
    - Manuscript draft of Observations in San Domingo by Cornelius Cole., 1869; 138pp. (Box 37, Folder 1)
    - Political record book, 1863-1872 (Box 37, Folder 2)
      Lists of names and addresses of persons, political contacts, office holders, editors in California.
    - Lists of addresses in California and Washington, D.C., including political persons in the Grant administration., c. 1860-1880; 5 pocket-size volumes; 2 unbound lists. (Box 37, Folder 3)
    - Autograph books. vol. 1870 (Box 37, Folder 4)
      Containing autographs of the members of the Senate in that year. vol. 1922-1923: birthday guests.
    - Papers and documents concerning the ancestry of Cornelius Cole and the genealogy of the Cole family., 4 pieces. (Box 37, Folder 5)
    - Positive photograph of Cornelius Cole's copy of the Emancipation Proclamation signed by Abraham Lincoln. (Box 37, Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous documents., 1859-1922 (Box 37, Folder 7)
      Included are copies of bills in the Senate and House of Representatives, Congressional Directory, 1893, printed copies of speeches by John Sherman, Montgomery Blair, Thaddeus Stevens, James A. Garfield, the Congressional Record, June 27, 1922 32 pieces.
  - Miscellaneous Documents, Clippings, and Maps
    - Documents concerning the Alabama claims., 2 pieces. (Box 62, Folder 1)
    - Documents concerning the Los Angeles Harbor controversy., 45 pieces. (Box 62, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous printed documents, reports, advertisements., 10 pieces. (Box 63, Folder 1)
    - Clippings concerning the senatorial campaign of A.G. Spalding., 1911-1912; 20 pieces. (Box 63, Othertype 2)
    - Clippings from California newspapers concerning the citrus industry and the lemon tariff, 1911; 36 pieces. (Box 63, Othertype 3)
    - Maps pertaining to Los Angeles harbor and to cities in Australia., 5 pieces. (Box 63, Othertype 4)
  - Scrapbooks Concerning Political Subjects and the Cole Family, 1833-1928; (Oversize)
    - Clippings from California and other newspapers., 1852-1860 (Box 38, Othertype 1)
      Concerning Fugitive Slave Act in California, Mark Hopkins, the Pacific railroad, election of 1860
    - Clippings from California and other newspapers,. concerning election of Cornelius Cole, administration of Andrew Johnson., 1865-1872 (Box 38, Othertype 2)
    - Clippings from California and other newspapers, 1854-1871 (Box 38, Othertype 3)
      Concerning membership of the Senate, Cornelius Cole's legislation, San Domingo, Chinese immigration, China Mail bill.
    - Clippings from California and other newspapers, 1851-1874 (Box 38, Othertype 4)
      Concerning California senatorial contest, the Pacific railroad, Australian Mail line, outbreak of the Civil War, wartime elections in California.
    - Clippings from California and other newspapers, 1871 (Box 38, Othertype 5)
      Concerning state politics.
    - Clippings from California and other newspapers and magazines (Box 38, Othertype 6)
      Concerning the World Columbian Exposition at Chicago and Olive Cole's activities in connection with it.
    - Clippings from California and other papers, 1833-1928; [Oversize-wrapped separately]. (Box 38, Othertype 7)
      Concerning general political subjects and members of the Cole family.
  - Invitations and calling cards from various persons., 1850-1924; 1500 pieces. (Box 39 and 64)
    Three envelopes of invitations and calling cards, some of them autographed, from most of the persons whose names or letters appear in the correspondence, including men in government and politics, and friends of the family.
  - Memorabilia
    - Memorabilia and objects concerning various persons and members of the Cole Family., 1850-1922; 85 pieces. (Box 40)
      Association pieces concerning Lincoln, Mt. Vernon, Virginia, Queen Victoria, John Jay, Cornelius Cole, Olive Cole, Frederick Cole, Gilbert M. Cole, William H. Taft, Charles E. Hughes, tickets to the impeachment of Andrew Johnson, University of Southern California, William Cole Burke, George R. Cole's watercolors.
    - Memorabilia concerning the European War., 1914-1918; 52 pieces. (Box 65)
      Pamphlets and mementos concerning American, British, Belgian and Italian propaganda and attitudes before and during the war.
    - Souvenirs of A.H. Jones's (C. Cole's Brother-In-Law) Trip to Europe. (Box 74)
  - Photographs
    - Photographs of members of the Cole family. (Box 66)
    - Photographs of friends of the Cole family. (Box 67)
    - Photographs of friends of the Cole Family and of various places, including California scenes., Approximately 400 pieces. (Box 68)
      The items in these boxes are mostly identified.
    - Photographs of members of the Cole family and of various persons., 1850-1943; 10 pieces. (Box 78)
      [Wrapped separately] Family photographs include: Laura and Jennie Burke, Emma Cole Burke, Cornelius Cole (including some Brady photos) David Cole, Frederick Cole, George R. Cole, George T. Cole, Olive Cole, Lucretia Cole, Schuyler Cole, Seward Cole, Willoughby Cole, Lourina Severns, Elijah Townsend, 44 pieces. Various persons: William S. Hart, Ulysses S. Grant, Abraham Lincoln, Tom Mix, Nazimova, Adelina Patti, Queen of Roumania, William H. Seward, Thaddeus Stevens. 22 pieces. Unidentified persons. 17 pieces. Various places: Eventide, the Cole home at Colegrove, Los Angeles, Hollywood Bowl, site of Sutter's mill, Mt. Vernon, Virginia, Taghannuk Falls, Cayuga Lake, New York, Wesleyan University.